<?xml version="1.0"?>
<datastewardship>
<chapter id="1" title="Design of experiment">
Before you decide to embark on any new study, it is nowadays good practice to consider all options to keep the data generation part of your study as limited as possible. It is not because we can generate massive amounts of data that we always need to do so. Creating data with public money is bringing with it the responsibility to treat those data well and (if potentially useful) make them available for re-use by others. So, given the research question you would like to address, a very first question should always be

<question id="1" bookid="1.1" title="Is there any pre-existing data?">
Are there any data sets available in the world that are relevant to
your planned research?
<expert name="Barend Mons" email="barend.mons@dtls.nl"/>
<answer label="No" responsetype="advice">
You know that this is very unlikely? This question is not only about
data sets that are similar to what you want to determine yourself, but
also reference data or data that should be mined from the existing
literature. Further, it is very likely that you will refer to related
data, e.g. other databases where you usually "quickly look something
up", but that could maybe be properly integrated, especially if you
need to do such lookups multiple times.
</answer>
<answer label="Yes" responsetype="followup">
<ask id="2"/>
</answer>
</question>
<question id="2" bookid="1.2" title="Will you be using any pre-existing data (including other people's data)?">
Will you be referring to any earlier measured data, reference data, or data that should be mined from 
existing literature? Your own data as well as data from others?
<answer label="No" responsetype="ok"/>
<answer label="Yes" responsetype="followup">
  <ask id="3"/>
  <ask id="9"/>
  <ask id="20"/>
  <ask id="21"/>
</answer>
</question>
<question id="3" bookid="1.3" title="Will you use reference data?">
Much of todays data is used in comparison with reference data. A
genome for instance is compared with a reference genome to identify
genomic variants. If you use reference data, there are several other
issues that you should consider.
<answer label="Yes" responsetype="followup">
<ask id="4"/>
<ask id="5"/>
<ask id="6"/>
</answer>
<answer label="No" responsetype="ok"/>
</question>
<question id="4" bookid="1.4" title="Where is it available?">
  Do you know where the reference data is available, what the
  conditions for use are, and how to reference it?
</question>
<question id="5" bookid="1.5" title="What format?">
  Do you know the data format of the reference data? Is this suitable
  for your work? Does it need to be converted?
</question>
<question id="6" bookid="1.6" title="Is it versioned?">
 Many reference data sets evolve over time. If the reference data set
 changes, this may affect your results. If different versions of a
 reference data set exist, you need to establish your
 "version policy".
 <answer label="Yes" responsetype="followup">
   <ask id="7"/>
   <ask id="8"/>
 </answer>
 <answer label="No" responsetype="ok"/>
</question>
<question id="7" title="Which version will you be using?">
If there are different versions available, you have to decide with all
project partners together which version you will be using. Probably
you will go for the latest release as of the date of the start of your
research project. However, if you have other data from older projects
that need to be merged, you may need to consider using the same
release you used for a previous project.
</question>
<question id="8" title="Will you change the reference when it is updated?">
If the reference changes while you are working on your research
project, you need to decide whether you will follow these
changes. Most likely that will mean that you have to do some analyses
again, so you will need to make sure enough resources are available to
do so. You can decide to stay with the version that you started with;
this can have the disadvantage that you will not benefit from added
information or added consistency.
</question>
<question id="9" bookid="1.7" title="Will you use any existing (non-reference) data
			sets?">
  Even if you will be producing your own data, you often will also be
  relying on existing data sets. You may need to integrate your new data
  with an existing data set or retrieve additional information from
  related data bases. Will you be doing such things?
  <answer label="Yes" responsetype="followup">
    <ask id="10"/>
    <ask id="14"/>
    <ask id="15"/>
    <ask id="17"/>
    <ask id="18"/>
    <ask id="19"/>
  </answer>
  <answer label="No" responsetype="advice">
    Did you research all the data that exists? You may not be aware of
    all existing data that could be available. Although using and/or integrating
    existing data sets may pose a challenge, it will normally be
    cheaper than collecting everything yourself. Even if you decide
    not to use an existing data set, it is better to do this as a
    conscious decision!
  </answer>
</question>
<question id="10" title="Will you be able to get access to the data?">
  For all data that is not your own, do you know who owns the data, and how to get access?
  Obviously, this question and the followup questions will need to be
  answered for every data set you plan to use.
  <answer label="Yes" responsetype="followup">
    <ask id="11"/>
    <ask id="12"/>
    <ask id="13"/>
  </answer>
  <answer label="No" responsetype="advice">
    I guess that means you will not be using the existing data anyway.
  </answer>
</question>
<question id="11" bookid="1.8" title="Will the owners of the existing data work
			 with you on your research?">
 Will you enter into a collaboration with the owners of the original
 data that you plan to use? Will they be available to help you with
 integration questions? Will they be linking their work to you?
</question>
<question id="12" bookid="1.9" title="Will a renewal of any informed consent be
			 needed?">
  If the data that you will re-use is coupled to people, Is the
  informed consent that was originally obtained from those people
  including your current research?
</question>
<question id="13" title="Are there usage restrictions that could be in
			 the way of your research?">
 What will you not be allowed to do with the existing data? Will this
 pose any problems to your project? How are you ensuring that you will
 adhere to the usage restrictions?
</question>
<question id="14" title="How will you access the data?">
  Will you have full access of the data (i.e. will you receive a copy)
  or will you be have access in another way (i.e. via a web site with
  restricted questions or by running your own analysis on the computer
  of the data owners? Will this be seamless for your research?
</question>
<question id="15" title="Is the existing data available in a format
			 that is identical to what you will be using
			 yourself?">
  Data formats can vary, and evolve. For each existing data source you
  need to ask yourself whether it has the same format as you are using
  yourself. Differences could also be in the terms used to fill in the
  data (e.g. are they using "cancer" or "malignant neoplasm"? or maybe
  a term from a different language?).
  <answer label="Yes" responsetype="ok"/>
  <answer label="No" responsetype="followup">
    <ask id="16"/>
  </answer>
</question>
<question id="16" bookid="1.10" title="Will you need to harmonize different sources
			 of existing data?">
  If you are combining data from different sources, harmonization may
  be required. You may need to re-analyse some original data.
</question>
<question id="17" title="Is the data you are re-using fixed? Or is it still actively updated?">
  If a data source that you are using is being updated over time, this
  can affect your results. You therefore need to decide what you will do when the
  data source changes: will you be able to keep using the same old version
  (documented) for all your analyses? Or will you always be using the
  latest version at any moment in time?
  Will you re-do any analysis if the source changes? How can you
  ensure reproducibility of your own results?
</question>
<question id="18" title="Is all of the data usable in its available
			 form?">
  Can you use all the data from the existing source in the form in
  which it is available? Or will you need to curate the data? Will you
  be making a subset? Can you make a subset easily? How will you
  document these efforts so that others can reproduce what you did?
</question>
<question id="19" title="Do you know what data exists?">
  Are you aware of all the existing data that you may be able to use?
  Are you confident that you know what you could use?
</question>
<question id="20" bookid="1.11" title="How will the existing data be integrated?">
  Who will do the work to integrate the existing data sources?
  Is it known how this needs to be done exactly?
</question>
<question id="21" bookid="1.11.1" title="Will you be gathering data from literature?">
  Will you be gathering data from the scientific literature?
  <answer label="No" responsetype="ok"/>
  <answer label="Yes" responsetype="followup">
    <ask id="22"/>
  </answer>
</question>
<question id="22" bookid="1.11.2" title="Will you be using text mining?">
  Will you be using text mining tools to get the data from the
  literature? Unless the data you are extracting is in one or a few
  tables in a few papers, you may need an expert in text mining
  literature data to be able to get a consistent result with a
  reasonable effort.
</question>
<question id="23" title="Do you need to link to different types of
			 data?">
  The power of data is unleashed when different sources containing
  different types of existing data are linked together. Will you be doing that?
  <answer label="No" responsetype="ok"/>
  <answer label="Yes" responsetype="followup">
   <ask id="24"/>
   <ask id="25"/>
   <ask id="26"/>
   <ask id="27"/>
   <ask id="28"/>
  </answer>
</question>
<question id="24" title="Will that need a project plan?">
  Unless the coupling is of a type that has been done numerous times
  before in similar ways, this kind of job can be tricky. It may be a
  good idea to have someone knowledgeable in this field check whether
  you need to take any special provisions.
</question>
<question id="25" title="What will you do if the coupled data is
			 updated?">
  If a data source that you are using is being updated over time, this
  can affect your results. You therefore need to decide what you will do when the
  data source changes: will you be able to keep using the same old version
  (documented) for all your analyses? Or will you always be using the
  latest version at any moment in time?
  Will you re-do any analysis if the source changes? How can you
  ensure reproducibility of your own results?
</question>
<question id="26" title="What will you do if the format is changed?">
 How will it affect your project if the format in which the original
 data is available is changed?
</question>
<question id="27" title="Are conversions needed?">
  Will you need to be performing a format conversion, translate items,
  or do you need to change the data you couple to to another nomenclature?
  In that case, make sure you plan enough time for this.
</question>
<question id="28" title="Will you link existing data or join them?">
  Will your coupling of existing data be a new data set that contains
  the relations between the two original data sets, and link back to
  the sources? Or will you ingest the data that you will be coupling
  and combine it into a single new source? This decision has
  implications for data ownership, data access, and for the burden of
  maintenance.
</question>
<question id="29" title="Are you creating reference data?">
  Will you be creating data that others will use as reference data
  later?
  <answer label="Yes" responsetype="followup">
    <ask id="30"/>
    <ask id="31"/>
    <ask id="32"/>
  </answer>
  <answer label="No" responsetype="ok"/>
</question>
<question id="30" title="What will the rules for use be?"/>
<question id="31" title="How will you maintain it?"/>
<question id="32" title="How will the release schedule be?"/>
<question id="33" title="Will you be storing data on biological samples?">
  Will you be doing biobanking?
  <answer label="Yes" responsetype="advice">
    <ask id="34"/>
  </answer>
  <answer label="No" responsetype="ok"/>
</question>
</chapter>
</datastewardship>
