<?xml version="1.0"?>
<datastewardship>
<chapter id="1" title="Design of experiment">
In this part of the data stewardship questionnaire, you will be asked
questions about the setup of your research.
<question id="1" title="Is there any pre-existing data?">
Are there any data sets available in the world that are relevant to
your planned research?
<expert name="Barend Mons" email="barend.mons@dtls.nl"/>
<answer label="No" responsetype="advice">
You know that this is very unlikely? This question is not only about
data sets that are similar to what you want to determine yourself, but
also reference data or data that should be mined from the existing
literature. Further, it is very likely that you will refer to related
data, e.g. other databases where you usually "quickly look something
up", but that could maybe be properly integrated, especially if you
need to do such lookups multiple times.
</answer>
<answer label="Yes" responsetype="followup">
<ask id="2"/>
</answer>
</question>
<question id="2" title="Will you be using any pre-existing data?">
Will you be referring to any earlier measured data, reference data, or data that should be mined from 
existing literature?
<answer label="No" responsetype="ok"/>
<answer label="Yes" responsetype="followup">
  <ask id="3"/>
  <ask id="9"/>
</answer>
</question>
<question id="3" title="Will you use reference data?">
Much of todays data is used in comparison with reference data. A
genome for instance is compared with a reference genome to identify
genomic variants. If you use reference data, there are several other
issues that you should consider.
<answer label="Yes" responsetype="followup">
<ask id="4"/>
<ask id="5"/>
<ask id="6"/>
</answer>
<answer label="No" responsetype="ok"/>
</question>
<question id="4" title="Where is it available?">
  Do you know where the reference data is available, what the
  conditions for use are, and how to reference it?
</question>
<question id="5" title="What format?">
  Do you know the data format of the reference data? Is this suitable
  for your work? Does it need to be converted?
</question>
<question id="6" title="Is it versioned?">
 Many reference data sets evolve over time. If the reference data set
 changes, this may affect your results. If different versions of a
 reference data set exist, you need to establish your
 "version policy".
 <answer label="Yes" responsetype="followup">
   <ask id="7"/>
   <ask id="8"/>
 </answer>
 <answer label="No" responsetype="ok"/>
</question>
<question id="7" title="Which version will you be using?">
If there are different versions available, you have to decide with all
project partners together which version you will be using. Probably
you will go for the latest release as of the date of the start of your
research project. However, if you have other data from older projects
that need to be merged, you may need to consider using the same
release you used for a previous project.
</question>
<question id="8" title="Will you change the reference when it is updated?">
If the reference changes while you are working on your research
project, you need to decide whether you will follow these
changes. Most likely that will mean that you have to do some analyses
again, so you will need to make sure enough resources are available to
do so. You can decide to stay with the version that you started with;
this can have the disadvantage that you will not benefit from added
information or added consistency.
</question>
<question id="9" title="Will you use any existing (non-reference) data
			sets?">
  Even if you will be producing your own data, you often will also be
  relying on existing data sets. You may need to integrate your new data
  with an existing data set or retrieve additional information from
  related data bases. Will you be doing such things?
  <answer label="Yes" responsetype="followup">
    <ask id="10"/>
    <ask id="14"/>
  </answer>
  <answer label="No" responsetype="advice">
    Did you research all the data that exists? You may not be aware of
    all existing data that could be available. Although using and/or integrating
    existing data sets may pose a challenge, it will normally be
    cheaper than collecting everything yourself. Even if you decide
    not to use an existing data set, it is better to do this as a
    conscious decision!
  </answer>
</question>
<question id="10" title="Will you be able to get access to the data?">
  Do you know who owns the data, and how to get access?
  Obviously, this question and the followup questions will need to be
  answered for every data set you plan to use.
  <answer label="Yes" responsetype="followup">
    <ask id="11"/>
    <ask id="12"/>
    <ask id="13"/>
  </answer>
  <answer label="No" responsetype="advice">
    I guess that means you will not be using the existing data anyway.
  </answer>
</question>
<question id="11" title="Will the owners of the existing data work
			 with you on your research?"/>
<question id="12" title="Will a renewal of any informed consent be
			 needed?"/>
<question id="13" title="Are there usage restrictions that could be in
			 the way of your research?"/>
<question id="14" title="How will you access the data?"/>
</chapter>
</datastewardship>
